HARRY WILD JONES:
Minnesota Historical Society
Harry Wild Jones Papers,
[undated] and 1884-1934.
Minnesota Historical Society
Jones, Harry Wild, 1859-1935.
Architectural drawings and plans, sketches of building facades, photographs, and project bidding specifications, all documenting a number of projects undertaken by Minneapolis architect Harry W. Jones.
3.0 cu. ft. (2 boxes and 2 oversize folders, unboxed).
BIOGRAPHY OF HARRY WILD JONES
Jones, the son of a Baptist clergyman, was born in Schoolcraft, Michigan on June 9, 1859. He attended Brown University for two years, then transferred to the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and graduated from MIT in 1882. He came to Minneapolis in 1883, where he established an architectural practice in which he remained for the rest of his career. Although Jones specialized in ecclesiastical architecture, he also designed many private residences and public and commercial buildings in the Minneapolis area, as well as in a number of other places around the United States.
ARRANGEMENT
These documents are organized into the following sections:
Miscellaneous Papers
Architectural Drawings
Oversize Materials
RELATED MATERIALS
The scrapbook is probably the first of a set, the rest of which were apparently donated to the Hennepin County Historical Society, Minneapolis.
CATALOG HEADINGS
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog of the Minnesota Historical Society. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Topics:
Church architecture--Designs and plans.; Commercial buildings--Minnesota--Minneapolis--Designs and plans.; Dwellings--Minnesota--Drawings.; Public architecture--Minnesota--Minneapolis--Designs and plans.; Church buildings--Minnesota--Drawings.; Architecture, Domestic--Designs and plans.
Places:
Minneapolis (Minn.)--Buildings, structures, etc.
Organizations:
Bethlehem Swedish Lutheran Church (Minneapolis, Minn.)--Pictorial works.; First Presbyterian Church (Hibbing, Minn.)--Pictorial works.; Northfield Methodist Episcopal Church (Minneapolis, Minn.)--Pictorial works.; St. Cloud Presbyterian Church (Saint Cloud, Minn.)--Pictorial works.; Simpson Methodist Episcopal Church (Minneapolis, Minn.)--Pictorial works.
Types of Documents:
Architectural records.
Occupations:
Architects--Minnesota--Minneapolis.
ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION
Accession Information:
Accession number: 4618
DETAILED DESCRIPTION
- Miscellaneous papers
  - Miscellaneous Papers, undated and 1924-1933. (1)
    Two folders of miscellaneous papers (undated and 1924-1933) contain several small-format architectural drawings, sketches, and photographs of buildings designed by Jones, as well as detailed bidding specifications for several of his Minneapolis projects: Hiawatha Park skating pavilion, White House restaurant, a Sunday school addition to the Fourth Baptist Church, and an addition to the Simpson Methodist Episcopal Church. These architectural materials are accompanied by a newspaper article (1933) containing Jones' recollections of early days in the Washburn Park area of Minneapolis
  - Drawings of church facades, undated.
    Black and white photographic prints of eight Jones designs mounted on matboard. They are accompanied by a watercolor sketch of the facade of the First Baptist Church in Rockwell City, Iowa.
  - Photograph, undated.
    A black and white photograph of an unnamed brick residence tentatively identified as being in Northfield, Minnesota.
  - Scrapbook, [1884-1931].; 1 volume.
    Contains many small-format architectural drawings, photographs, sketches, and newspaper accounts of buildings designed by Jones. Most are churches, but the volume also includes private residences, apartment buildings, public buildings, and commercial structures in Minneapolis and several other cities. One cyanotype photograph depicts the aftermath of the 1894 Minneapolis Lumber Exchange fire.
- Architectural Drawings
  - George A. Hormel home, Austin, Minn., undated.; Blueprints. 9 sheets. (2)
    - Basement plan., 1.
    - First floor plan., 2.
    - Second floor plan., 3.
    - First floor plan, revised., 4.
    - Second floor plan, revised., 5.
    - Basement plan, revised., 6. (2)
    - Basement plan., 7.
    - First floor plan., 8.
    - Second floor plan., 9.
  - Yale Bowl seating plan, New Haven, Conn., undated.; Blueprint. 1 sheet.
    - Overview., 1.
  - Lake Nokomis shelter building, Minneapolis, 1929.; Blueprints. 8 sheets.
    - Foundation plan., 1.
    - First floor plan., 2.
    - South West elevation., 3.
    - North East elevation., 4.
    - North, west, south, east elevation and section thru., 5.
    - Details., 6.
    - Detail of porch columns., 7.
    - Entrance detail., 8.
  - Bryant Square field house for Minneapolis Park Board blueprints, 1924.; Blueprints. 9 sheets. (2)
    - Foundation plan., 1.
    - Floor plan., 2.
    - South elevation., 3.
    - North elevation, 4.
    - West and east elevation., 5.
    - Details., 6.
    - Details of doors and windows., 7.
    - Floor plan., 8.
    - Head piping detail., 9.
  - Hiawatha Park shelter building, Minneapolis, 1932.; Blueprints. 8 sheets.
    - Foundation plan., 1.
    - Floor plan., 2.
    - Northeast elevation., 3.
    - Southwest elevation., 4.
    - Northwest and southeast elevations., 5.
    - Details., 6.
    - Heating plan., 7.
    - Floor plan, approved., 8.
  - White House Restaurant, Minneapolis, 1928.; Blueprints. 6 sheets.
    - Front elevation, floor plan, section thru., 1.
    - Right, left, and rear elevation and section thru., 2.
    - Details., 3.
    - Front elevation, floor plan, section thru., 4.
    - Right, left, and rear elevation and long and cross section., 5.
    - Details., 6.
  - Lyndale Park, Linden Hills, Minneapolis, 1916.; Blueprint. 1 sheet.
    - Overview plan.
  - Unidentified basement plan, undated.; Blueprint. 1 sheet.
    - Basement plan., 1.
  - Prayer's Addition to Minneapolis: Lot 3, Block 2, undated.; Blueprint. 1 sheet.
    - Overview., 1.
  - Christ English Lutheran Church, Minneapolis, 1915.; Blueprints. 10 sheets. (2)
    - Basement plan., 1.
    - First floor., 2.
    - 31st Street elevation., 3.
    - Oliver Street elevation., 4.
    - Rear elevation., 5.
    - Side elevation., 6.
    - Transverse section., 7.
    - Trussing., 8.
    - Scale details of door and trim., 9.
    - Roof plan., 10.
  - First Baptist Church, Hastings, Minn., 1923.; Blueprints. 12 sheets.
    - Excavation plans., 1A.
    - Basement plans., 1.
    - First floor., 2.
    - Front elevation., 3.
    - 8th Street elevation., 4.
    - Rear elevation., 5.
    - Left end elevation., 6.
    - Transverse section thru tower., 7.
    - Longitudinal section., 8.
    - Transverse section thru tower., 9.
    - Details., 10-12.
  - Knox Presbyterian Church, [n.p.], undated.; Blueprint. 1 sheet. (2)
    - First floor plan., 1.
  - Windom Park Baptist Church, [n.p.], 1909.; Blueprints. 9 sheets.
    - Basement plan., 1.
    - First floor plan., 2.
    - Front elevation., 3.
    - Side elevation., 4.
    - Rear elevation., 5.
    - Side elevation., 6.
    - Longitudinal section., 7.
    - Cross section., 8.
    - Amended plans., 9.
  - First Norwegian Danish Baptist Church, Minneapolis, 1917.; Blueprints. 15 sheets.
    - Excavation and footing plan., 1.
    - Basement plan., 2.
    - First floor plan., 3.
    - Second floor plan., 4.
    - 16th Avenue elevation., 5.
    - 13th Street elevation., 6.
    - Side elevation., 7.
    - Rear elevation., 8.
    - Cross section., 9.
    - Longitudinal section., 10.
    - Roof truss., 11. (2)
    - Section thru tower., 12.
    - Details of window and wall section., 13.
    - Basement., 14.
    - Heating plans., 15.
  - Lynnhurst Congregational Church, Minneapolis, undated.; Blueprints. 4 sheets.
    - Front elevation., 1.
    - Sub-basement plan., 2.
    - First floor., 3.
    - Basement plan., 4.
  - Presbyterian Church, Bemidji, Minn., undated.; Blueprint. 1 mounted sheet.
    - First floor plan., 1.
  - Northfield Methodist Church, Northfield, Minn., 1920.; Blueprints. 18 sheets.
    - Basement plan., 1.
    - First floor plan., 2.
    - Second floor plan., 3.
    - Front elevation., 4.
    - Right and left elevation., 5.
    - Left end elevation., 6.
    - Rear elevation., 7.
    - Half-cross and longitudinal section., 8.
    - Details of tower., 9.
    - Detail of auditorium trusses., 10. (2)
    - Trusses., 11.
    - Details., 12.
    - Window details., 13.
    - Details., 14-15.
    - Frame details., 16.
    - Rostrum and choir loft., 17-18.
  - Northfield Methodist Episcopal Church, Northfield, Minn., 1921.; Blueprints. 21 sheets.
    - Basement plan., 1.
    - Auditorium floor plan., 2.
    - Balcony plan., 3.
    - South elevation., 4.
    - East elevation., 5.
    - West elevation., 6.
    - North elevation., 7.
    - Longitudinal and transverse section., 8.
    - Trusses., 9.
    - Window section., 10. (2)
    - Balcony window., 11.
    - Main entrance door details., 12.
    - Cornice details., 13.
    - Details of tower., 14.
    - Two column details., 15.
    - Baluster base and post detail., 16.
    - Stairs, balcony, and auditorium details., 17.
    - Details., 18.
    - Elevation of upper part of choir loft., 19.
    - Details of pulpit., 20.
    - Details., 21.
  - First Baptist Church, Brainerd, Minn. Addition, 1921.; Blueprints. 16 sheets.
    - Basement plan., 1.
    - First floor., 2.
    - Second floor., 3.
    - North elevation., 4.
    - East elevation., 5.
    - South elevation., 6.
    - West elevation., 7.
    - Transverse section., 8.
    - Longitudinal sections., 9.
    - Tower., 10.
    - Auditorium windows., 11. (2)
    - Windows in tower., 12.
    - Details., 13-16.
  - Advent Christian Church, Minneapolis, 1926.; Blueprints. 12 sheets.
    - Basement floor plan., 1.
    - First floor., 2.
    - Roof plan., 3.
    - West elevation., 4.
    - South elevation., 5.
    - Rear elevation., 6.
    - Side elevation., 7.
    - Longitudinal section., 8.
    - Transverse section., 9. (2)
    - Window and door section., 10.
    - Details., 11-12.
  - Tentative plans for unidentified Baptist church, 1930.; Blueprints. 3 sheets.
    - Second floor plans., 1.
    - First floor., 2.
    - Basement., 3.
  - Congregational Church, Wayzata, Minn., 1921.; Blueprints. 12 sheets.
    - Basement plan., 1.
    - First floor., 2.
    - Front elevation, 3.
    - South elevation., 4.
    - North elevation., 5.
    - East elevation., 6.
    - Transverse section., 7.
    - Longitudinal section., 8.
    - Details of basement window frames., 9.
    - Details of doors and windows., 10.
    - Details of window., 11.
    - Truss details., 12.
  - First Presbyterian Church, Hibbing, Minn., 1926.; Blueprints. 58 sheets.
    - Locking device for silver drawers., 1.
    - Full exterior., 2.
    - Seating and pew ends., 3.
    - Organ chamber., 4.
    - Organ., 5.
    - Iron cross., 6.
    - Revised kitchen plan., 7-8.
    - Basement floor plan., 9.
    - First floor., 10.
    - Auditorium seating plan., 11. (2)
    - First floor plan [early?], 12.
    - Basement floor plans., 13.
    - Fixture dimension., 14.
    - Fixture details., 15-17.
    - Details of tower foundation and pier and column., 20.
    - First floor plan., 21.
    - Second floor plan., 22.
    - East elevation., 23.
    - North elevation., 24.
    - South elevation., 25.
    - Rear elevation., 26.
    - Temporary elevation., 27.
    - Longitudinal section., 28.
    - Section towards chancel., 29.
    - Details of cast stone window tracery, 30. (2)
    - Section towards balcony., 31.
    - Half elevation of tower., 32.
    - Window detail., 34.
    - Details of truss and cornice., 35.
    - Details of doors and rails., 36.
    - Kitchen details., 37.
    - Details of lectern, communion table, organ grille, chancel., 38.
    - Stair and pew detail., 39.
    - First floor., 40.
    - First floor., 41.
    - Second floor., 42.
    - Connections to basement radiators., 43.
    - Basement plan., 44.
    - First floor plan., 45.
    - Second floor plan., 46.
    - Organ grille, corrected detail., 47.
    - Pew detail., 48.
    - Details of communion table., 49.
    - Plan of platform., 50.
    - Cornerstone detail., 51. (2)
    - Alteration of kitchen arrangement., 52.
    - Revised kitchen plan., 53.
    - Cabinet details., 54.
    - Mounted sketch of church [broken]., 55.
    - Chancel furniture details., 56.
    - Stone inscriptions., 57-58.
  - Shanghai College Chapel, undated.; Studies. 10 sheets.
    - Front elevation [?]., 1.
    - Rear elevation [?]., 2.
    - Main floor plan., 3.
    - Front facades [?]., 4-10.
  - Front Facade of unidentified church, undated.; Study. 1 sheet.
  - Bishop Whipple Memorial Christ Church, Minneapolis, undated.; Blueprints/studies. 11 sheets.
    - Blaisdell Ave. elevation., 1.
    - First floor sketch., 2.
    - 37th Street front., 3.
    - First floor plan., 4.
    - Basement floor plan., 5.
    - First floor plan., 6.
    - Exterior facade., 7-8.
    - Auditorium layout., 9.
    - Transverse section., 10.
    - Exterior facade., 11.
  - Columbia Heights Methodist Episcopal Church, Minneapolis, 1920.; Blueprints. 16 sheets. (2)
    - Plot and excavation plan., 1.
    - Ground floor plan., 2.
    - First floor., 3.
    - Central Ave. and front elevation., 4.
    - Tower addition., 4A.
    - North and east addition., 5.
    - Longitudinal and part cross plan., 6.
    - Details of truss and girders., 7.
    - Details of doors., 8.
    - Details of sills, casements, porch., 9.
    - Details of windows., 10.
    - Details of choir loft and rostrum., 11.
    - Details of pews and cupboards., 12.
    - Gould Ave. elevation., 13.
    - Main floor plan., 14.
    - Basement plan., 15.
    - Lot 26-28 elevation., 16.
  - Community Methodist Episcopal Church [n.p.], 1922.; Blueprints. 12 sheets.
    - Basement floor plan., 1.
    - First floor., 2.
    - Front elevation., 3.
    - Left end elevation., 4.
    - Rear elevation., 5.
    - Right end elevation., 6.
    - Transverse and tower section., 7. (2)
    - Longitudinal section., 8.
    - Details of cornice, truss, windows., 9.
    - Details of windows., 10.
    - Details of doors., 11.
    - Details of pulpit, communion table, stairway., 12.
  - Pine City Methodist Episcopal Church, Pine City, Minn., undated.; Sketches. 4 sheets.
    - Front elevation., 1.
    - Front elevation [different]., 2.
    - First floor., 3.
    - Second floor., 4.
  - Grace Methodist Episcopal Church, Minneapolis, 1921.; Blueprints. 13 sheets.
    - Excavating, footing, and basement plan., 1.
    - First and second floor plan., 2.
    - Front and side elevation., 3.
    - Left and rear elevation., 4.
    - Half cross and longitudinal section., 5.
    - Main tower detail., 6.
    - Elevation of joints., 7.
    - Details of window and right elevation., 8.
    - Details of doors., 9.
    - Details of kitchen cupboards and girders., 10.
    - Half plan of choir loft and rostrum., 11.
    - Details of communion table, pulpit, pew, stairs., 12.
    - Revised balcony details., 13.
  - Lake Park Baptist Church, St. Paul, Minn., 1931.; Blueprints and specifications. 10 sheets plus specs. (2)
    - Basement floor plan., 1.
    - Main floor., 2.
    - West elevation., 3.
    - South elevation., 4.
    - East elevation., 5.
    - North elevation., 6.
    - Transverse section looking towards chancel., 7.
    - Section towards balcony and balcony plans., 8.
    - Basement plans., 9.
    - Main floor., 10.
  - Universalist Church, Owatonna, Minn., 1905.; Blueprints. 14 sheets.
    - Basement plans., 1.
    - First floor., 2.
    - Roof plan., 3.
    - North plan., 4.
    - East elevation., 5.
    - West elevation., 6.
    - South elevation., 7.
    - Longitudinal elevation., 8.
    - Cross section., 9.
    - Section A-A., 10.
    - Plan of framing base of dome, tower section., 11. (2)
    - Elevation showing organ front., 12.
    - Organ loft., 13.
    - Seating plan., 14.
  - Bethelhem Swedish Lutheran Church, Minneapolis, 1927.; Blueprints. 57 sheets.
    - Foundation and sub-basement plan., 1.
    - Basement plan., 2.
    - Pier and buttress details., 3.
    - First floor., 4.
    - Second floor., 5.
    - Roof plan., 6.
    - South elevation., 7.
    - West elevation and details of cut stone panels., 8.
    - North elevation., 9.
    - Rear elevation., 10.
    - Transverse section., 11. (2)
    - Longitudinal section., 12.
    - Tower detail., 13.
    - Pastor's window and basement entrance., 14.
    - Choir loft and auditorium windows., 15.
    - Chancel window., 16.
    - Elevation of truss., 17.
    - Auditorium wall section., 18.
    - Details and section thru tower., 19.
    - Details., 20.
    - Chancel details., 21.
    - Details of pulpit and choir screen., 22.
    - First floor seating plan and pew end., 23.
    - Plan of kitchen., 24.
    - Details of pulpit and bookcases., 25.
    - Window details., 26.
    - Drawing of choir loft and organ., 27.
    - Sub-basement plan., 28.
    - Basement plan., 29.
    - First floor., 30.
    - Second floor., 31. (2)
    - Basement plan, (1924).; 32.
    - First floor, (1924).; 33.
    - Second floor, (1924).; 34.
    - Transverse of chancel and plan of chancel., 35.
    - Sketch of second floor., 36.
    - Second floor plan., 37.
    - Basement., 38.
    - First floor., 39.
    - Drawing of communion table [?]., 40.
    - Plans for organ., 41-42.
    - Details of organ case., 43.
    - Drawing of Chancel., 44.
    - Detail of organ case., 45.
    - Details of organ grill., 46.
    - Details for Crown Iron Works Co., 47-57.
  - Design for a Model Baptist Church, undated.; Blueprints. 3 sheets. (2)
    - Basement., 1.
    - First floor., 2.
    - Second floor., 3.
  - Certificate from Gov. John A. Johnson, 1924.
    Appointing Jones architect for the State Art Society.
- Oversized Material
  - YWCA Building (proposed additions), Austin, Minn., undated.; Sketches. 6 sheets. (Folder 1)
    - First floor plans., 1.
    - Side elevation [?]., 2-5.
    - Front elevation, lower, and upper floor plan., 6.
  - Glenwood Park, Minneapolis. Topographical survey, 1933.; Blueprint. 1 sheet.
    - Overview., 1.
  - Robbinsdale School, Minneapolis, undated.; Blueprint. 1 sheet.
    - Balcony girder., 1.
  - Washburn Park standpipe, Minneapolis, undated.; Blueprints. 5 sheets.
    - Band spacing on walls., 1.
    - Details., 2-4.
    - Detail of cupola., 5.
  - St. Cloud Presbyterian Church, St. Cloud, Minn., 1916.; Blueprints. 23 sheets.
    - Basement and foundation plans., 1.
    - First floor plan., 2.
    - Roof plan., 3.
    - Front elevation., 4.
    - Side elevation [?], 5.
    - Rear and west elevations., 6.
    - Cross and longitudinal section., 7. (Folder 1)
    - Section thru tower and door details., 8.
    - Half elevation, section of center line, half plan of choir., 9.
    - Elevation and details of truss., 10.
    - Window details and section thru main cornice., 11.
    - Detail of front elevation and section thru tower., 12.
    - Door details., 13.
    - Basement window details., 14.
    - Heating plan for basement., 15.
    - Heating for first floor., 16.
    - Seating plan., 17.
    - Back of center seat., 18.
    - Full size detail of carved brackets on organ case., 19.
    - Chancel elevation showing choir stalls, pulpit, reading desks..., 20.
    - First floor plan., 21.
    - Choir and pulpit detail., 22.
    - Colored drawing of #20, 23.
  - Messiah Evangelical Lutheran Church, Minneapolis, 1916.; Blueprints. 12 sheets. (Folder 2)
    - Foundation and basement plan., 1.
    - First floor plan., 2.
    - Second floor plans., 3.
    - Front elevation., 4.
    - East and west elevation., 5.
    - Rear elevation., 6.
    - Longitudinal section., 7.
    - Details of windows in basement., 8.
    - Cross section., 9-10.
    - Tower entrance., 11.
    - Windows in auditorium., 12.
  - Fourth Baptist Church, Sunday School Addition, Minneapolis, 1916.; Blueprints. 8 sheets.
    - Foundation plan., 1.
    - First floor plan., 2.
    - Second floor plans., 3.
    - Fremont St. elevation., 4.
    - North side elevation., 5.
    - West (rear) elevation., 6.
    - Longitudinal section., 7.
    - Traverse section and entrance details., 8.
  - Burmese Baptist Church, Moulmein, Burma, 1921.; Blueprints. 9 sheets.
    - Plot plan., 1.
    - Ground floor., 2.
    - Auditorium floor plan., 3.
    - Front elevation., 4.
    - Right side elevation., 5.
    - Rear elevation., 6.
    - Left side elevation., 7.
    - Transverse section., 8.
    - Longitudinal section., 9.
  - Simpson Methodist Episcopal Church, Minneapolis. Additions, 1924.; Blueprints. 25 sheets. (Folder 2)
    - Basement plan., 1.
    - First floor plan., 2.
    - Second floor plan., 3.
    - Roof plan., 4.
    - East and south elevation., 5.
    - West and north elevation., 6.
    - Transverse and longitudinal section., 7.
    - Longitudinal and sub-basement., 8.
    - Chancel details., 9.
    - Plan of kitchen., 10.
    - Main stairway., 11.
    - Plan of kitchen., 12.
    - Cornerstone sketch., 13.
    - Mechanical equipment plans., 14-19.
    - Erection plan., 20-25.